Guide to the Raymond C. Battalio and John B. Van Huyck Papers, 1949-2014, bulk 1972-2014 RL.11714
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1983-2009; 1
  - Email Correspondence, 1993-2009
    - Eudora, 1997-2004; 2 files; approximately 13 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0002, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0003)
      Personnel restriction until 2074.
      Correspondents include Ray Battalio, David Cooper, and Alvin Roth, among others. Topics include research and experiments.
    - Eudora, 1997-2004; 18 files; approximately 222 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0002, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0004)
      Correspondents include Ray Battalio, Ken Binmore, David Cooper, Herschel Grossman, Charles Holt, John Kagel, David Levine, Thomas Palfrey, Charles Plott, Alvin Roth, Larry Samuelson, Beth Seely, Chad Wade, and William Zame, among others. Attachments include draft writings and research material on experimental work with Battalio and others.
    - Eudora, 2003; 2 files; approximately 3 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0001, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0001)
      Correspondence with Ray Battalio, personal correspondence with family members, and other communications.
    - Jack.fol, 2003-2004; 1 file; less than 1 megabyte. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0002, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0003)
      Backup copy of email messages.
    - Jvh.econmail, 2004-2006; 3 files; approximately 135 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0002, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0004)
      Personnel restriction until 2076.
      Correspondents include Ray Battalio, David Cooper, John Kagel, Charles Plott, Beth Seely, and Chad Wade, among others. Topics include Battalio's early work using rats in behavioral experiments.
    - Minbox, 1994-1996; 446 files; approximately 1 megabyte. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0001, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0001)
      Email messages in individual text files.
    - Mn, 1997; 2 files; approximately 2 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0001, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0001)
      Correspondents include Ray Battalio, John Kagel, Alvin Roth, and Larry Samuelson, among others.
    - Msentbox, 1993-1996; 351 files; less than 1 megabyte. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0001, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0001)
    - Neo.tamu.edu, 2002-2009; 3 files; approximately 1.2 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0002, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0004)
      Personnel restriction until 2079.
      Correspondents include Amy Glass, Brit Grosskopf, Charles Holt, John Kagel, Jana Lambert, David Levine, Charles Plott, Alvin Roth, Vernon Smith, Roberto Weber, and William Zame, among others. Topics include planning for the Battalio commemorative conference. Attachments include research material on experimental work with Battalio and others.
    - Netscape, 1996; 2 files; less than 1 megabyte. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0001, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0001)
      Correspondents include David Levine, Larry Samuelson, and others.
    - Other.mai, 1997-2003; 15 files; approximately 52 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0001, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0001)
      Correspondents include Ray Battalio, Ken Binmore, Colin Camerer, David Cooper, Vince Crawford, David Levine, Thomas Palfrey, Charles Plott, Alvin Roth, Larry Samuelson, and William Zame, among others. Topics include editorial work for Games and Economic Behavior, and there is personal correspondence with family members. Attachments include research material on experimental work with Battalio, graduate students, and others.
    - Pinbox, 1993-1994; 140 files; less than 1 megabyte. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0001, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0001)
    - Popsent, 1993-1994; 70 files; less than 1 megabyte. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0001, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0001)
    - Supporting Files, 1995-2003; 1,390 files; approximately 154 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0001, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0001)
      Unsorted email attachments and other files related to email correspondence.
    - Supporting Files, 1995-2004; 38 files; approximately 3 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0002, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0003)
    - Supporting Files, 1995-2004; 123 files; approximately 4 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0002, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0004)
    - Zip, 1996; 1 file; approximately 2 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0001, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0001)
      Correspondents include Ray Battalio, Charles Holt, David Levine, Thomas Palfrey, Charles Plott, Alvin Roth, and Larry Samuelson, among others.
    - Zip9704, 1996-1997; 2 files; approximately 5 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0001, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0001)
    - Zip9706, 1996-1997; 2 files; approximately 3 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0001, Box 80, Disk RL11714-IHD-0001)
- Conferences and Consulting, 1984-2009; 1
  Material such as correspondence, presentation material, programs/agendas/schedules, and travel documents related to Battalio and Van Huyck's conference and workshop participation and Van Huyck's consulting activities. The largest files are on the Allied Social Science Associations (ASSA), Economic Science Association (ESA), National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER), and National Science Foundation (NSF). Organized into two subseries: Conferences and Consulting.
  - Conferences, 1984-2009; 1
    Includes correspondence, presentation material, programs/agendas/schedules, and travel documents. The largest files are on the Allied Social Science Associations (ASSA), Economic Science Association (ESA), and National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER). Arranged alphabetically by name of organization.
    - Accounting Mini-Conference, undated (Box 14)
      Program and presentation material for conference at University of Minnesota.
    - Adaptive Behavior, 1992; 2 folders (Box 3)
      Presentation material for paper on adaptive behavior.
    - Allied Social Science Associations (ASSA), 1985-2003; 14 folders (Box 3)
      Presentation material, notes, travel documents, and other documents related to conferences.
    - Arizona Trip, 1995 (Box 3)
      Travel documents.
    - Arne Ryde Symposium, undated (Box 3)
      Discussion papers
    - Asset Markets, 1992 (Box 3)
      Presentation material.
    - Bargaining Conventions, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Barnett Conference, 1987 (Box 3)
      Schedule for conference on economic complexity.
    - Battalio Memorial Conference, 2006; 4 folders (Box 14)
      Programs, papers, and other material on organizing conference in honor of Battalio.
    - Behavioral Decision Research in Management, 1990-1992; 2 folders (Box 3)
      Correspondence.
    - Bonn Workshop, 1997 (Box 3)
      Itinerary for conference on bounded rationality.
    - Brown University and University of Pittsburgh, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Carnegie-Rochester Conference, 1986-1991; 2 folders (Box 3)
      Schedule and other material for conference on public policy.
    - Commitment v. Discretion, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Conferences Electronic Files, 1993-1996; 602 files; approximately 95 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0003)
      Text and spreadsheet files; folders for AEA, Arne Ryde Symposium, ASSA, Cal Tech, CMU, EEA, ESA, Faculy Development Leave, GMU, Harvard, Michigan, MPS, Pittsburgh, Plugin-Hybrid Vehicles Workshop, SEA, TAMU, UCLA, USC, and Wisconsin.
    - Coordination Failures Workshop, 1989 (Box 3)
      Notes and travel documents for workshop at University of Iowa.
    - Dynamic Econometric Modeling, 1986 (Box 3)
      Pamphlets and schedules for conference at University of Texas at Austin.
    - Eastern Economic Association, 2000 (Box 3)
    - Econometric Society, 1985-2002; 6 folders (Box 3)
      Notes, travel documents, and schedules for meetings and summer workshops.
    - Economic Science Association (ESA; 1-30 of 32), 1988-2005 and undated; 30 folders (Box 3)
      Presentation material, notes, travel documents, and schedules for annual conferences, as well as material related to Van Huyck's service on Executive Committee.
    - Economic Science Association (ESA; 31-32 of 32), 1994-2009; 2 folders (Box 14)
      Conference files and documents from service on journal committee.
    - Edwin Smart Symposium, 1988-1989; 2 folders (Box 4)
      Notes and schedules for conferences on games and economic behavior and macroeconomics and game theory.
    - European Economic Association (EEA), 1987 (Box 4)
      Cancelled trip.
    - FMME Presentation, 1988 (Box 4)
      Notes on stochastic replanning and signalling games.
    - Focal Points, Lund, Sweden, 1997 (Box 4)
      Travel documents and schedule for conference on coordination, complexity, and communication in strategic contexts.
    - Game Theory in Behavioral Sciences, 1995 (Box 4)
      Travel documents, schedules, and correspondence related to conference in Tucson, Arizona.
    - Harvard University and California Institute of Technology (Cal Tech), 1999 (Box 4)
    - Harvard University, 1999 (Box 4)
    - International Association for Research in Economic Psychology (IAREP)/Society for Experimental Economics (GEW): EconPsych and Expt. Econ, 1992 (Box 4)
      Call for papers.
    - International Seminar on Macroeconomics (ISOM), 1985 (Box 4)
      Schedule and correspondence.
    - International Symposium on Evolutionary Dynamics and Nonlinear Economics, 1989; 3 folders (Box 4)
      Schedule and presentation material.
    - Is Reputation a Substitute for Commitment in the Peasant-Dictator Game, 1996-1997; 2 folders (Box 4)
      Presentation material for talks given at Brown, Penn State, Pittsburgh, Michigan, an ESA conference, and a SEA conference.
    - Learning Equilibrium Behavior, 1994 (Box 4)
      Presentation material for conference at TAMU.
    - Liberty Fund Series on Political Economy, 1987 (Box 4)
      Correspondence on identifying potential participants for conference.
    - Lone Star Conference, 1992-1998; 6 folders (Box 4)
      Draft presentations and schedules for conferences for Texas-based economists.
    - Median Presentation, undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Min Rule, undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Presentations, undated (Box 4)
      Unlabeled presentation material.
    - Mont Pelerin Society (MPS), 1996-2008; 3 folders (Box 4)
      Schedules, readings, and travel documents.
    - National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER), 1986-1995; 10 folders (Box 4)
      Programs, presentations, notes, and correspondence for summer institutes.
    - New Orleans 2001 (Box 4)
    - New York University (NYU)/Dallas Fed Trip, 1991 (Box 4)
      Travel documents and correspondence.
    - Operations Research Society of America (ORSA)/The Institute of Management Sciences (TIMS), 1992 (Box 4)
      Program and travel documents.
    - Order Statistic Games--Behavior in Games, New York City, NY and Learning Equilibrium Behavior, College Station, TX, 1993-1994 (Box 4)
      Presentation material for conferences.
    - Origin of Conventions, 1995-1996; undated; 4 folders (Box 4)
      Presentation material for multiple versions of papers on the origin of conventions in coordination problem games, learning, and bargaining games.
    - Pennsylvania State University, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Pittsburgh: Working Conference, 1990 (Box 4)
      Notes and travel documents.
    - Rice University, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Rutgers/NYU, 1995 (Box 4)
      Travel documents and correspondence for talks given at department workshops.
    - Secrecy Presentation, undated (Box 4)
      Presentation material for unknown conference.
    - Selection Dynamics, Learning Equilibrium Behavior, 1994 (Box 4)
      Presentation material for conference on learning equilibrium behavior at TAMU.
    - Selection Dynamics... Incomplete Information, undated (Box 4)
    - Similar Games, Michigan, 2001 (Box 4)
      Presentation material for speaking engagement at University of Michigan.
    - Social Science Research Council, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
      Schedule and correspondence for conference on monetary research.
    - Society for the Advancement of Behavioral Economics (SABE) Conference, 1988 (Box 4)
      Correspondence on conference proposal submission.
    - Southern Economic Association (SEA), 1987-2008; 7 folders (Box 5)
      Presentation material, notes, travel documents, and schedules for multiple meetings.
    - Stony Brook Summer Institute on Game Theory, 1990-1995; 3 folders (Box 5)
      Notes, schedules, and correspondence for workshop series.
    - Strategic Similarity, 1997-1998 (Box 5)
      Presentation material for speaking engagements at Arne Ryde Symposium and University of Pittsburgh Theory Seminar.
    - Texas Agricultural and Mechanical University (TAMU) Conference, 1995 (Box 14)
      About organizing a conference on equilibrium selection and learning.
    - Texas Conference on Monetary Economics, 1994-1995; 2 folders (Box 5)
      Agendas and correspondence.
    - University of California Los Angeles (UCLA), 1999 (Box 5)
      Travel documents for research-related visit.
    - University of Michigan, 2001 (Box 5)
    - University of Minnesota: Accounting Minicamp, 1991 (Box 5)
      Schedule for "Game Theory in Experiments" workshop.
    - University of New Mexico, 1987 (Box 5)
      Paperwork related to speaking engagement.
    - University of Pennsylvania, 1990 (Box 5)
      Schedule, notes, and travel documents for "Behavior in Games" conference.
    - University of Southern California and University of Pittsburgh, 2000 (Box 5)
    - University of Texas at Austin, Game Theory Conference, 1992; 1996; 2 folders (Box 5)
      Notes and correspondence.
    - University of Virginia and Virginia Tech, 2003 (Box 5)
    - University of Wisconsin, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Warsaw International Meeting, 1987 (Box 5)
      Schedules for conference on "New Frontiers in Economic Policy."
    - Washington University, 1998 (Box 5)
      Notes, travel documents, and schedule for conference on "Experimental Economics Research on Bargaining and Learning."
    - Western Economic Association, 1989-1990 (Box 5)
      Schedule and travel documents.
    - Wisconsin, 1995 (Box 5)
    - Original Microcassette, Wisconsin, undated (Box 79, Audio-cassette RL11714-MCS-0010)
    - Workshop on Games and Behavior in Honor of Amnon Rapoport, 1996 (Box 5)
      Notes, schedule, and correspondence.
  - Consulting, 1993-1996; 2
    The vast majority of these files are Van Huyck's evaluations of National Science Foundation (NSF) proposals as part of his service on review panels, but he also consulted on one legal case. Arranged alphabetically.
    - Consulting Electronic Files, 1995; 153 files; approximately 11 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0003)
      Text files; entirely relates to NSF.
    - National Science Foundation (NSF), 1994-1996; 5 folders (Box 64)
      Proposal evaluations.
    - Sibley Report, 1993 (Box 64)
      Van Huyck consulted on questions of milk pricing and cartel practices for legal case involving Kroger and Texas.
- Writings, 1972-2014; 1
  Material such as correspondence, drafts, supporting research material, referee reports, and reprints related to Battalio and Van Huyck's published and unpublished writings. The largest files are on "Dynamic Monetary Control and Interest Rate Stabilization," "Evidence on Learning in Coordination Games," and "Optimization Incentives and Coordination Failure in Laboratory Stag Hunt Games." Organized into three subseries: Articles and Book Chapters, Referee Reports, and Special Issue of Experimental Economics in Honor of Battalio.
  - Articles and Book Chapters, 1972-2014; 1
    Includes correspondence, drafts, reprints, and supporting research material (typically experiment data). The largest files are on "Dynamic Monetary Control and Interest Rate Stabilization," "Evidence on Learning in Coordination Games," and "Optimization Incentives and Coordination Failure in Laboratory Stag Hunt Games."
    Battalio and Van Huyck coded their experiments to indicate type and vintage (see the Experiments series for more details). Experiment codes appearing in this subseries also appear in the Experiments series, possibly allowing connections to be made between published writings and experiment files. The most frequently used codes are as follows: BB are beauty contest games inspired by Keynes's famous example of the workings of financial markets; C or CONV followed by a number are experiments on conventions; CR or CRAW followed by a number are coordination games; DEC followed by a letter and/or number or DX followed by a number are on decentralized allocation decisions; and PD followed by a number are peasant-dictator games. Less frequently used codes can be found in the Other Experiments and Realted Materials subseries.
    - A Retrospective on the Classical Gold Standard, 1921-1931: A Review Essay, 1986-1987 and undated; 3 folders (Box 5)
      Reprint, drafts, and notes.
    - A Taxonomy of Two by Two Games, 2003; 2 folders (Box 5)
      Drafts, notes, and research material.
    - Adaptive Behavior and Coordination Failure, 1990-1997; 5 folders (Box 5)
      Reprint, drafts, proofs, notes, and research material.
    - Adaptive Behavior and Coordination Failure Electronic Files, 1991-1995; 118 files; approximately 3 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0004, Box 66, Disk RL11714-FL3-0012, Disk RL11714-FL3-0013, Box 71, Disk RL11714-FL3-0724)
    - Articles and Book Chapters Electronic Files, 1986-2006; 596 files; approximately 125 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0004)
      Text, dataset, and image files; zipped folders.
    - Asset Markets as an Equilibrium Selection Mechanism, 1993 (Box 5)
      Reprint.
    - Bob Dole's School Choice Initiative, 1997 (Box 5)
      Drafts and notes.
    - Central Bank Secrecy, Interest Rates, and Monetary Control, 1990-1993 and undated; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Coastal Economic Development, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
      Drafts and research material.
    - Commitment versus Discretion in the Peasant-Dictator Game (1-4 of 8), 1993-1995; 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Commitment versus Discretion in the Peasant-Dictator Game (5-8 of 8), 1995; 4 folders (Box 6)
      Reprint, drafts, proofs, and research material.
    - Contributions and Crowd-Out of Public Goods, 2004-2008; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Contributions and Crowd-Out of Public Goods Electronic Files, 2001-2006; 142 files; approximately 3 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11714-SET-0004, Box 66, Disk RL11714-FL3-0001, Box 76, Optical-disc RL11714-OP-0001)
      Image and text files.
    - Coordination Failure in Market Statistic Games, 1998 (Box 6)
      Draft.
    - Credible Assignments and Coordination Failure in Laboratory Public Goods Games, 2001-2005; 3 folders (Box 6)
      Reprint and drafts.
    - Credible Assignments in Coordination Games, 1992 (Box 6)
    - Crowding-Out of Public Goods, 2010 (Box 6)
      Drafts.
    - Decentralized Competition, Pecuniary Externalities, and Allocative Efficiency, 1989; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Does Playing Against an Error Prone Opponent Influence Learning in Nim, 2014 (Box 6)
    - Does Seeing More Deeply into a Game Increase One's Chances of Winning, 2001-2006; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Dynamic Monetary Control and Interest Rate Stabilization, 1986-1989; 8 folders (Box 6)
      Reprint, drafts, notes, research material, and correspondence.
    - Equilibrium Selection in Observable Games, 1990 (Box 6)
    - Equilibrium Selection in Repeated Market Games, 1989 (Box 6)
    - Equity, Efficiency, and Security in Tacit Bargaining Games, 1989 (Box 6)
    - Estimating Bounded Rationality and Pricing Performance Uncertainty, 1995-2007; 4 folders (Box 6)
      Reprint, drafts, notes, and research material.
    - Eureka Learning, undated (Box 6)
    - Evidence on Learning in Coordination Games (1-8 of 10), 1995-2003; 2 folders (Box 6)
      Notes and research material.
    - Evidence on Learning in Coordination Games (9-10 of 10), 1993-2007; 8 folders (Box 7)
      Reprint, proofs, notes, and research material.
    - Evidence on the Equivalence of the Strategic and Extensive Form, 2001-2003; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Form Representation, 2002 (Box 7)
      Research material and correspondence.
    - History's Role in Coordinating Decentralized Allocation Decisions, 1992 (Box 7)
    - How Does an Opponent's Skill Level Influence Learning in Perfect Information Games, 2009 (Box 7)
    - Interest Bearing Money, Hyperinflation, and Default in the Republic of Texas, 1988 and undated; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Is Reputation a Substitute for Commitment in the Peasant-Dictator Game, 1994-2003; 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Market Concentration, Price Dispersion, and Inefficient Cross-Hauling in the Laboratory, 2005-2014 (Box 7)
    - Multiple Markets and Units: Theory, 1989 (Box 7)
      Draft and notes.
    - Nominal Sovereign Debt, Risk Shifting, and Reputation, 1984-1993; 6 folders (Box 7)
    - On the Origin of Convention: Evidence from Coordination Games, 1993-1997; 5 folders (Box 8)
      Reprint, drafts, research material, and correspondence.
    - On the Origin of Convention: Evidence from Symmetric Bargaining Games, 1992-1995; 6 folders (Box 8)
      Reprints, drafts, notes, and research material.
    - Optimization Incentives and Coordination Failure in Laboratory Stag Hunt Games, 1995-2001; 8 folders (Box 8)
    - Preferences, Demographics, and Games, 2009 (Box 8)
    - Prudence, Justice, Benevolence, and Sex, 1997-2002; 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Seigniorage, Inflation, and Reputation, 1984-1986; 4 folders (Box 9)
    - Selection Dynamics and Adaptive Behavior without Much Information, 2002-2007; 2 folders (Box 9)
      Reprint, drafts, and correspondence.
    - Selection Dynamics, Asymptotic Stability, and Adaptive Behavior, 1991-1993; 3 folders (Box 9)
      Reprint, draft, research material, and correspondence.
    - Sovereign Debt as a Contingent Claim, 1984-1988; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Strategic Similarity and Emergent Conventions, 1997-2000; 4 folders (Box 9)
    - Strategic Uncertainty, Equilibrium Selection, and Coordination Failure in Average Opinion Games, 1990-1991; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Tacit Cooperation, Strategic Uncertainty, and Coordination Failure, 1992-2002; 5 folders (Box 9)
    - Tacit Coordination Games, Strategic Uncertainty, and Coordination Failure, 1990 (Box 9)
    - What Does it Take to Eliminate the Use of a Strategy Strictly Dominated by a Mixture, 1994-1999; 4 folders (Box 9)
      Reprint, draft, notes, research material, and correspondence.
    - A Note on the Distribution of Earnings and Output per Hour in an Experimental Economy, 1978 (Box 10)
    - A Stochastic Helicopter Money Model, 1981 (Box 10)
    - A Test of Consumer Demand Theory Using Observations of Individual Consumer Purchases, 1973 (Box 10)
    - A Test of the Cycle of Poverty Hypothesis, 1986; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - An Empirical Analysis of Individual Disequilibrium Labor-Supply Behavior, 1990 (Box 10)
    - An Experimental Investigation of Consumer Behavior in a Controlled Environment, 1974 (Box 10)
    - An Experimental Test of a Simple Theory of Aggregate Per-Capita Demand Functions, 1976 (Box 10)
    - Adaptive Behavior and Coordination Failure, 1990-1993; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Animals' Choices Over Uncertain Outcomes, 1985 (Box 10)
    - Animals' Choices Over Uncertain Outcomes: Further Experimental Results, 1991 (Box 10)
    - Assessment of Error in Concurrent Records of Income and Expenditure in Token Economies, undated (Box 10)
    - Asset Markets as an Equilibrium Selection Mechanism, 1992-1993; 2 folders (Box 10)
      Reprint and research material.
    - Asset Markets Can Select a Product Market Equilibrium, 1988 (Box 10)
      Draft and research material.
    - Central Bank Secrecy, Interest Rates, and Monetary Control, 1988-1990; 2 folders (Box 10)